Good morning everybody. Before we start,
we pick up on 31b. Today's דף daf is ל"ב עמוד ב',
32 amud bet, but we pick up on 31b. And we had
been discussing the issue about whether שחיטה shechita is valid without intention
and brought into a larger discussion about whether חולין chullin non-sanctified matters
are valid without intention. The גמרא Gemara extended it to cases like
טבילה. tevilah. You always wonder when the גמרא Gemara broadens the discussion
how broad to go. Clearly there are different acts. I mean there's
a whole discussion of מצוות mitzvos require
intention. Presumably there's a whole series of different types of acts you
can do in the non-קדשים kodshim field in which intention may or
may not matter. But the גמרא Gemara is at least generalizing it
and it said that even those that say that טבילה tevilah requires
intention, at least שחיטה shechita is different and they quoted a verse
from which we learned that שחיטה shechita was different and did not
require it. So now we are going to focus on what type
of intention we are or are not talking about. So take a
look.
רבנן. Rabbanan.
It is 1, 2, 3, 4,
5... דברים י"ב Devarim Yud Bet in the left-hand margin, about two
lines above that. The end of the line where it says רבנן
מהי. Rabbanan michee. Okay so that's where we are, about three lines
above that. רבנן Rabbanan and the rabbis who say that
intention is required for שחיטה, shechita, right? They were the ones that
said that if you were throwing knives at a wall it is
not a good שחיטה. shechita. So how would they explain why intention
is required if the תורה Torah only demands כוונה kavana by sacrifices?
Implicitly it's not required by non-sacrifices.
So here's what they would respond: נהי דלא בעינן כוונה לזביחה, Nechee
delo ba'inan kavana lizevicha,
okay you don't require intention for shechting, but לחתיכה בעינן. l'chatichah ba'inan.
You do require כוונה kavana for cutting. Now what type of cutting
are we referring to? It could just mean an act of cutting,
so it could be that the rabbis say if you're trying to
cut a gourd, let's say, and you thought that this little skin
skinny thing in front of you was a gourd and it turned
out to be a chicken neck,
that that's okay because at least you were trying to cut. Or,
right, or it could mean תוספות Tosafot suggests that it could mean
you have to know you're cutting סימנים. simanim. You have to
know you're cutting the trachea and the esophagus, you just don't necessarily
have to intend that this is going to have the halachic impact
of שחיטה shechita and of making the meat permissible. But the point
here is that there's a whole range of different intentions. And this
is true for example, by just to give a simple analogy, by
the גמרא's Gemara discussion about מצוות צריכות כוונה. mitzvos tzrichos kavana. Do
מצוות mitzvos require intention? And the גמרא Gemara quotes a couple of
cases where it says like somebody's walking behind a שול shul and
hears a שופר shofar blowing. If he intends, he's יוצא. yotze. So
says doesn't this prove מצוות mitzvos require intention? So the גמרא Gemara
says no no no. That might mean that he's not confusing it
with like a cow mooing or something or a donkey braying. He
understands that it's a sound of a שופר, shofar, but that doesn't
mean you have to intend to do the מצווה. mitzvah. So there's
all different ranges of what type of intention. And the most basic
is to be aware of the physical act that you're doing. So
like be aware that you are actually eating מצה, matzah, not necessarily
to be יוצא yotze the מצווה, mitzvah, but just you don't think
that it's a cracker or being aware that you are hearing a
שופר shofar and not hearing a donkey. So if you have even
less than that intention, that's normally considered to be מתעסק. misasek. That's
at the end, even less than that it's completely incidental what you're
doing, it doesn't connect to you in any way because you're not
even aware physically what it is. Beyond that you know physically what
it is but you don't necessarily understand its import. You're not intending
to do a מצווה. mitzvah. You're not intending it to be effective
as שחיטה. shechita. So that's the type of distinction the גמרא Gemara
is making here. That the רבנן Rabbanan might say yes, you know,
it's true that you don't need full intention, you don't have to
intend for it to be שחיטה, shechita, but you still must basically
know you're cutting, or at least cut maybe even cutting סימנים, simanim,
but you don't have to know it's שחיטה. shechita. So that's understandable.
The biggest חידוש chiddush is רבי נתן Rabbi Natan who the גמרא
Gemara said yesterday we rule like, that said that completely incidental, you
accidentally drop a knife, you're playing darts and you happen to shecht
and that's good. That is of course the biggest חידוש chiddush because
those cases we would normally call מתעסק, misasek, that it's completely involved
in something else, what happened was completely incidental, and even so רבי
נתן Rabbi Natan who we apparently rule like is saying that that's
good. So that is of course a huge idea, an extreme statement
that you need like according to רבי נתן Rabbi Natan no כוונה.
kavana. Here the רבנן Rabbanan are saying you at least need, you
don't need full כוונה kavana but at least you need כוונה kavana
to do the physical act. And now the גמרא Gemara is going
to continue and spell out the implications. So let's take a look.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says: בהא זיכנו Bahaza kinu
רבי נתן לרבנן. Rabbi Natan lerabbanan. Here רבי נתן Rabbi Natan sort
of beat the rabbis in terms of his position having better proof.
How? מי כתיב וחתכת? Mi ksiv vechatachta? If it were written and
you shall cut... didn't say that you shall cut. וזבחת כתיב. Vezavachta
ktiv. It says you shall שחט. shecht. So that's what the פסוק
pasuk demands. So the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is demanding
a full act of שחיטה, shechita, meaning כוונה kavanah for all components,
even כוונה kavanah that accounts as שחיטה. shechita. So make up your
mind. אי בעינן כוונה לחתיכה, I beinan kavanah lachaticha, if you're going
to demand כוונה kavanah for cutting, אפילו זביחה נמי ליבעי. afilu zvicha
nami libei. So you should require full, meaning the תורה Torah demands
an act of שחיטה. shechita. So if כוונה kavanah is required, there's
no way you should split your vote. You should require כוונה kavanah
not just for cutting but for a full act of שחיטה, shechita,
that it should count to make the meat permissible. אי לא בעינן
כוונה לזביחה, I lo beinan kavanah lizvicha, and if you're going to
say you don't require כוונה kavanah for it to count as שחיטה,
shechita, so לחתיכה נמי לא ליבעי, lachaticha nami lo libei, you shouldn't
even require כוונה kavanah for cutting. So the תורה Torah demands that
it be an act of שחיטה. shechita. If you say that that
means that you need כוונה kavanah for it, so כוונה kavanah has
to be as שחיטה, shechita, not just as cutting. If you're not
going to demand כוונה kavanah as שחיטה, shechita, then why should you
demand כוונה kavanah for anything? Now again, the response is relatively obvious
as I said, based on other points of the גמרא, Gemara, that
if you don't have כוונה kavanah for even the physical act, then
it doesn't even connect to you. You're completely מתעסק. mitasek. It's completely
incidental. Okay, so it's completely understandable to say you need כוונה kavanah
for the physical act, so at least you've done the act. Maybe
you didn't define it as שחיטה, shechita, you weren't thinking about שחיטה,
shechita, but at least you could say you've done the act. But
here the גמרא Gemara is making the claim: either all or nothing.
What is this middle position? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says now:
היכי דמי נדה שנאנסה וטבלה? Heichi dami niddah shenensa vetavla? We're going
back to a case we had yesterday about a נדה niddah who
went into the מקוה mikvah against her will, by force, and that
was a case where she had no כוונה. kavanah. So what's the
case? The גמרא Gemara says: אילימא דאנסה חברתה ואטבלה, Ilima de'antza chavarta
veatbla,
if her friend forced her and they grabbed her and threw her
into the מקוה, mikvah, so כוונה דחברתה כוונה מעליא היא. kavanah dechavarta
kavanah mealya hi. Her friend's כוונה kavanah counts as כוונה. kavanah. Now
again, that's not so clear, right? If the תורה Torah demands that
I do an act of טבילה, tvilah, so even if you took
me and you dunked me, we could say you were מטביל matbil
me, right, you immersed me, but it doesn't necessarily say that
I immersed, I immersed myself. Why should we assume that just because
me is the subject
doing an act, can be replaced by me becoming the object and
you having an intention to the act? It's not necessarily the same,
right? You could certainly understand that the תורה Torah might demand that
in theory, if the תורה Torah demands that I do a conscious
act of טבילה, tvilah, right, and I define it as being going
to the מקוה, mikvah, that that be my intention that matters, not
if somebody else dunks me in the מקוה. mikvah. But the גמרא
Gemara here is assuming that that can be transferred. It's similar to
the assumption the גמרא Gemara had before that if you have your
vessels there and I am sitting with כוונה, kavanah, that should count
even though I'm not doing anything to the vessels, that we can
sort of shift the locus, the locus of כוונה. kavanah. What?
Unless you have no negative כוונה, kavanah, you're simply having no כוונה?
kavanah?
It could be, it could be. I'm just saying it's not as,
right, it's not as transparently obvious as the גמרא Gemara would have
it. Okay, I don't know. ועוד בתרומה נמי אכלה. Ve'od bitruma nami
achla. And but because we have actually evidence that it's true, but
it's not just logically true. That works even for תרומה, truma, if
somebody makes somebody else go to the מקוה. mikvah. How do you
know that?
דתנן, Detnan, we have in a משנה: Mishna: החרשת והשוטה והסומא, Hachereshet
vehashoteh vehasuma, a woman who is a חרשת, chereshet, שוטה, shoteh, or
סומא, suma, meaning either deaf mute or not sane or blind. Blind
being relevant here because part of the issue is not just intelligence
and דעת da'at but the ability to check oneself if one is
still bleeding.
ושנתטרפה דעתן, Veshenitrefa da'atan, or a woman not of right mind. So
how do they check themselves if they're bleeding or not? So אם
יש להן פקחות, im yesh lahen pichos, if they have friends that
are well, in by intellect and by sight, מתקנות אותן, metaknot otan,
they literally fix them, meaning they can help them do their own
internal check and determine whether they're bleeding or not. And then
מתקנות אותן ואוכלות בתרומה, metaknot otan ve'ochlot bitruma, then they can go
to the מקוה mikvah and eat תרומה. truma. So the emphasis of
this משנה Mishna is more about who checks to make sure whether
she's still bleeding or not, but the point is, okay, she stops
bleeding, how does she go to the מקוה? mikvah? And again, assuming
similar to the חרש שוטה וקטן cheireish shoteh vekaton bar משנה, Mishna,
that their own intention is not considered intention, so therefore the intention
obviously here that is considering it a valid טבילה tvilah is the
fact that it is the friends that are helping her go to
the מקוה. mikvah. Now again, that is not necessarily what the משנה
Mishna says and also, because as we said the other day, חרש
שוטה וקטן cheireish shoteh vekaton does maybe have full intention but it
doesn't mean they have no intention, and these women certainly intend to
go into the water, at least the physical act of intention. So
anyway, the גמרא Gemara is reading this as: look, you see that
if somebody else intends for them and assists them in the process
or forces them in the process that counts. So that's not the
full case of נאנסה. nensa. Although again, that could be debated. Let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So אמר רב פפא לאביי,
Amar Rav Pappa le'Abaye, so here's the example of how she went
to the מקוה mikvah without intention, לרבי נתן, lebi Natan, according to
רבי נתן Rabi Natan whose example of no intention means literally no
intention, not even for the physical act, here's the example. Example, she
fell off of a, she fell off of a, of a bridge.
Okay? She was walking on a, by a river, which would have
been a good מקווה. mikvah. She fell off a bridge, hopefully it
was a low bridge, didn't get hurt, okay? In deep water, and
there she fell into water, you weren't even intending to go into
water. So that's a case that you didn't even intend for the
physical act. לרבנן, l'Rabbanan, the Rabbis who speak about you need intention
for the physical act, but not for its halakhic implications, שיורדה להקר,
sheyarda l'haker, she went into a river to cool off, she went
swimming, isn't it the case?
What? Yeah,
I mean okay, so went for inside in the circumstances, not for
by others. Okay? So she went to go swimming without intention to,
for it to count as a טבילה. tevilah. So this is a
nice demonstration of how the גמרא Gemara applies conceptually, again abstracts and
generalizes the debate. There's a general debate, there's a debate by שחיטה,
shechitah, do you require no intention or intention for the physical act?
And we're going to assume that that's a more general debate of
what type of intention is required for various acts that change status
in non-kodshim areas. So for רבי נתן Rabbi Natan zero intention, the
act could be completely incidental, which is a huge חידוש, chiddush, and
we normally would call that מתעסק. mitasek. And for the Rabbis you
at least need the intention for the physical act, and they're applying
that then to טבילה. tevilah.
Yeah, and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan fits in better in the לשון
lashon of נסה. nessa. Right. That is true. Anyway, but is שוטה
shotah a congenital condition as opposed to ניתקפה דעתה, nitkafa datah, which
may be temporary sometimes?
Yeah, that's a good point. Normally the גמרא Gemara doesn't distinguish.
Yeah, ניתקפה דעתה nitkafa datah can be temporary, but the גמרא Gemara
even by שוטה shotah speaks about נשתטה nishtata and נשתפה nishtafa becoming
a שוטה, shotah, so I'm not sure why it distinguishes here.
I mean the גמרא Gemara in חגיגה Chagigah has very specific indicators
for what constitutes שוטה, shotah, ניתקפה דעתה nitkafa datah might be more
generic, but I'm not sure,
I'm not sure. Okay, all right, yeah, so let's keep on going.
All right, so that's the end of that debate about what different
levels of כוונה kavanah and really speaks to the extreme of רבי
נתן's Rabbi Natan position. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now we're going to
talk about not exactly a כוונה kavanah issue but something else that
can invalidate, but not שחיטה shechitah by שחיטה shechitah of a פרה
אדומה. parah adumah. Let's take a look. שחט פרה ושחט בהמה אחרת
עמה, Shachat parah v'shachat behemah acheret imah, it'll be an interesting application
of the כוונה kavanah discussion. Somebody שחטed shachat the פרה אדומה parah
adumah and שחטed shachat another animal at the same time. Actually it's
like the case of our משנה, mishnah, שחטing shachat two animals with
one act, right? Both necks are lying in front of you, one
long knife, you שחט shachat both. Now by פרה אדומה, parah adumah,
their principle is is that ושחט אותה ולא אותה וחברתה v'shachat otah
v'lo otah v'chavertah that you cannot do. There's two problems by פרה
אדומה, parah adumah, רש״י Rashi points this out. One is doing a
מלאכה אחרת, melachah acheret, doing some other מלאכה, melachah, some other type
of activity at the same time. But רש״י Rashi says based on
the continuing גמרא Gemara that that's only if you are conscious of
that other activity, intending that other activity, because then it's a problem
of not having your full one hundred percent focus on the פרה.
parah. Let's say you are one hundred percent focused on the פרה,
parah, you're not intending to do any other act. But by accident
and incidentally, this is how we're going to describe this case, you
happen to be שוחטing shochet another cow. They're both lying there, you're
only focused on the one in front of you, you weren't, the
whole point was you weren't paying attention to anything else that was
going on and there happened to have been another cow and you
שחט shachat it. That's a separate פסול, psul, not of focusing on
another activity, but ושחט אותה ולא אותה וחברתה. v'shachat otah v'lo otah
v'chavertah. You have to שחט shachat it and not any other animal
at the same time. Okay? So that is the concern here, that
you שחטed shachat another animal at the same time. So let's take
a look. אמר רבא שחט פרה ושחט בהמה אחרת עמה, Amar Rava
shachat parah v'shachat behemah acheret imah, you שחטed shachat them both at
the same time with intention for both, לדברי הכל פסולה, l'divrei hakol
psulah, everybody would agree it's invalid. Top of ל״ב עמוד א׳. Lamed
Bet Amud Aleph. נשחטה בהמה אחרת עמה, Nishchata behemah acheret imah, if
it happened, meaning you didn't intend it, you were focusing on the
פרה parah and you happened to be שוחטing shochet also another cow
at the same time. So the question is going to be did
that accidental שחיטה shechitah of the other cow, was it a good
שחיטה shechitah or not? So that's the debate of רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan and the Rabbis. לרבי נתן, l'Rabbi Natan, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
says a שחיטה shechitah without intention is good, so the other cow
is שחטed. shachat Because the other cow was a good שחיטה, shechitah,
the פרה parah is no good, because now you שחטed shachat another
cow at the time of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So לרבי
נתן, l'Rabbi Natan, according to רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, פרה פסולה, parah
psulah, the פרה אדומה parah adumah is invalid, בהמה כשרה, behemah kesherah,
the other animal is כשר. kosher. Because the other animal is כשר,
kosher, was a good שחיטה, shechitah, that made the פרה parah invalid.
And for the Rabbis it's the reverse: לרבנן פרה כשרה, l'Rabbanan parah
kesherah, the פרה אדומה's parah adumah okay. Why? Because בהמה פסולה, behemah
psulah, because the other animal was no good because it was unintended.
Okay, now by the way this is not so obvious, because remember
the Rabbis who argue on רבי נתן Rabbi Natan said all you
need was כוונה לחתוך. kavanah lachatoch. And here you do have כוונה
לחתוך kavanah lachatoch the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you just don't have
כוונה לחתוך kavanah lachatoch the other thing that's part of because it's
a long knife. So that's a חידוש chiddush that according to the
Rabbis that's insufficient כוונה, kavanah, you need כוונה לחתוך kavanah lachatoch the
thing you're cutting, not just to be cutting something else. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, that's all obvious. It's not obvious to
us, but okay, it's obvious. So the גמרא Gemara says נשחטה בהמה
אחרת לרבי נתן איצטריכא ליה. nishchata behemah acheret l'Rabbi Natan itztricha lei.
No, the חידוש chiddush is is when the animal got שחטed shachat
incidentally for רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. סלקא דעתך *Salka da'atach*, I might
have thought ושחט אותה אמר רחמנא *v'shachat osah amar Rachamana*, you should
שחט shecht *shecht* it, ולא אותה וחברתה *v'lo osah v'chavertah*, not it
and another animal, which is exactly why it's a problem for רבי
Rebbe, נתן *Rebbi Nosson*. היכי דמי *Heichi dami*, but I might have
thought what's the case where that's a problem? היכי דמי *Heichi dami*,
כגון ששחט שתי פרות בהדי הדדי *k'gon sheshachat shtei paros bahadi hadadi*,
maybe that says don't שחט shecht *shecht* two פרה אדומות *parah adumahs*
at the same time? אבל בהמה beheima, דחולין אימא eima, לא *Aval
behemah d'chullin eima lo*, but maybe if it's a non-sanctified animal, you
know, a normal animal, maybe it's not a problem, קא משמע לן
*kamashma lan* that it is. Okay, so again for רבי נתן *Rebbi
Nosson*, since you didn't intend a second animal, for the for רבי
נתן *Rebbi Nosson*, it's still a good שחיטה shechita *shechitah*. That makes
the פרה אדומה *parah adumah* no good. For the rabbis, the second
one is not a good שחיטה shechita? *shechitah*, even though you're intending
to שחט shecht *shecht*. Since you're not intending to שחט shecht *shecht*
it, it's not a good שחיטה shechita, *shechitah* for the second animal,
which allows the פרה אדומה *parah adumah* to remain good. Now finally,
one last application: חתך דלעת עמה *chatach d'la'as imah*, if you while
you were שחטינג shechting, *shechting* the פרה אדומה *parah adumah*, you said,
oh, great opportunity and you're going to be also cutting your gourd,
put the gourd next to פרה אדומה *parah adumah*, might as well,
so no, that in that invalidates because you're intending to do something
else. And again, intending another מלאכה *melachah* invalidates it. נחתכה דלעת עמה
*Nechtechah d'la'as imah*, if incidentally a gourd got cut with it, so
it's not a problem of doing another מלאכה *melachah* because you're not
intending for another מלאכה *melachah*. Is it a problem for אותה ולא
אותה וחברתה *osah v'lo osah v'chavertah*, only שחט shecht *shecht* one? No,
because it's not שחטינג shechting *shechting*, it's cutting. So דברי הכל כשירה
*divrei hakol kesherah*, everybody would agree that's good. Because you didn't intend
for the gourd, it's not doing another מלאכה *melachah*. How about the
fact that in practice something else got cut? That's not a problem.
The problem is only if something else got שחטד shechted, *shechted*. If
something else got cut, that would not invalidate the פרה אדומה *parah
adumah*. Okay, so we end that with a fun little application of
the rabbis and רבי נתן *Rebbi Nosson*. But again, the big issue
here is that by שחיטה shechita, *shechitah* you need כוח גברא *koach
gavra*, you need the energy of a person, right? Falling off the
table is not good. But the big חידוש chiddush *chiddush* is that
according to רבי נתן *Rebbi Nosson*, you don't require any intention, not
even intention to cut, it can completely be what we would normally
call מתעסק *mis'asek*. You could accidentally drop your knife, and even so
that would be valid. Yes, Charlie.
Usually in a dispute between a single sage and a collective group
of תנאים Tannaim *tana'im*, right?
We go by the חכמים *chachamim*. We go by the majority. Yeah,
here it was just because the person that taught רבי נתן *Rebbi
Nosson* said הוא תני לה הוא אמר לה הלכה halacha כרבי נתן
*hu tani lah, hu amar lah, halachah k'Rebbi Nosson*. Which raises an
interesting question, that just because you know there's one... there's one... רבי
אושעיא *Rebbi Oshaya*, whatever, there's you know, there's one אמורא *amora* that
rules like רבי נתן *Rebbi Nosson*. A, you can ask why did
he choose to rule like רבי נתן *Rebbi Nosson*? And B, the
question is just because he ruled like it doesn't mean everybody else
ruled like it. But you know, but so you're right, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did not ever vote any oppositional voices, you know,
anybody else that disagreed with it. So it is not clear always
why we, you know, why we will sometimes choose to go like
it. I mean, you could look at the textual evidence, I mean
that presumably the reason is because the סתם משנה Mishnah *stam Mishnah*
is being read. Both the first סתם משנה mishna. *stam Mishnah* of
חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh shoteh v'katan*, and this סתם משנה mishna, *stam
Mishnah* that if the knife falls off the table, right, which would
suggest that if it fell from a person, it is good. Both
of those סתם משניות *stam Mishnahs* sound like רבי נתן *Rebbi Nosson*.
So that presumably is what's in what's, you know, is what's pushing
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to say that. Okay, so now we are
going to get to another case of falling knives, but leading to
the another פסול psul *psul* which is the פסול psul של שהייה
shehiya. *psul of shehiyah*. So let's take a look at this next
משנה mishna *Mishnah*. נפלה סכין והגביהה *Naflah sakin v'higbi'ah*. So you were
שחטינג *shechting*. Now this is not your knife fell and did a
שחיטה shechita *shechitah*. You were in the middle of שחטינג *shechting* and
you dropped your knife in the middle. So you had to pick
it up and go continue your שחיטה shechita *shechitah*. So it's going
to be a problem of שהייה shehiya *shehiyah*, of pausing. או נפלו
כלים והגביהן *Or naflu kelim v'higbi'ah*. You were שחטינג *shechting* and you
know, your something, your כיפה *kippah* fell off or your wallet fell
out of your pocket or something. So you stopped your שחיטה shechita
*shechitah* to stop and pick it up. Okay. השחיז את הסכין ועף
*Hischit et hasakin v'af*, or you had right before you שחטד shechted
*shechted* you had spent time sharpening your knife, which is a very
sort of exerting activity. So you were very tired and in the
middle of שחיטה shechita *shechitah* you grew faint and you weren't able
to finish. ובא חבירו ושחט *U'ba chaveiro v'shachat*. So some friend took
over for you. So the point about all these are these are
all scenarios where you might have paused in the middle of your
שחיטה shechita *shechitah*. So what's the הלכה halacha. *halachah*? This is the
פסול psul של שהייה shehiya *psul of shehiyah*. אם שהה כדי שחיטה
shechita פסולה *Im shah k'dei shechitah, psulah*. If you paused the time
it takes to do another שחיטה shechita, *shechitah*, it's invalid. רבי שמעון
אומר אם שהה כדי ביקור Rabbi Shimon omer im sheha k'dei bikur.
*Rebbi Shimon omer im shah k'dei bikur*. No, not the time it's
required to do a שחיטה shechita, *shechitah*, a much smaller time or
presumably smaller time it takes to check your knife. I don't know,
maybe that's actually a longer time. I always assumed that was a
shorter time, because but really שחיטה shechita, *shechitah* is very quick. I
mean if you know what you're doing, שחיטה shechita. *shechitah* is like
a second. So checking a knife is presumably actually a slower thing.
So actually that's interesting.
It's showing you to the חכם chacham.
*chacham*. Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say, it's assume
you're the חכם *chacham*, for you yourself to check the knife. Okay,
but that's actually, I had always somehow assumed that that was a
shorter time, but but that might very well be a longer time.
Now this idea about the time it takes to do the activity
is a general type of a שיעור shiur, *shiur*. Like every הלכה
halacha *halachah* is different, but in general, when we say pausing is
a problem, often the pausing is, forget שחיטה shechita, *shechitah*, in all
other areas of מלאכה *melachah*, the time it takes to do that
activity. So for example, let's say, now pausing is not always a
problem. For example,
let's say... But other times it is, like let's say I'm reading
the מגילה Megillah, and I take an hour break in the middle
and then I resume. Or I'm reading the שמע Shema and I
take an hour break in the middle and then I resume. Issues
like that or שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, right? If I break in
the, take a pause and then I resume. So classically isn't the
הלכה halacha is not always the same in all areas. Some areas
as I said pausing is not a problem and even if it
is how long of a pause? But the general assumption when pausing
is a problem is the time it would take to do the
whole activity. If I pause in the middle of the מגילה, Megillah,
the time it would take to read the whole מגילה, or I
pause in the middle of שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, the time it
would take to say the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, then that is
considered to be a break. A shorter pause is not considered to
be a break as enough to consider to be like a continuous
activity. So if you understand that, this is not actually then a
special שחיטה shechita. הלכה. halacha. It's a generic הלכה halacha of what
is considered to be something that breaks up a process. What type
of a break? Except of course for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who
gives a different שיעור, shiur the amount it takes to check the
knife, which is not the classic שיעור shiur of the amount it
takes to do the activity. Okay so let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. But now we'll also see in the גמרא Gemara that
how exactly you define the time it takes is not so clear.
מאי כדי שחיטה? mai k'dei shechita? What to how do you measure
the amount of time it takes to do a שחיטה? shechita. אמר
רב כדי שחיטת בהמה אחרת. Amar Rav k'dei shechitas beheima acheres. The
time it takes to שחט shecht another animal, you know, not to
finish your שחיטה, shechita. but the time it takes to do a
full act of שחיטה, shechita. to if you were to שחט shecht
another animal, how long would it take? אמר ליה רב כהנא ורב
אשי לרב, Amlei Rav Kahana ve-Rav Ashi le-Rav, so they said to
רב, Rav, what do you mean by another animal? כדי שחיטת בהמה
לבהמה ועוף לעוף? k'dei shechitas beheima le-beheima ve-of le-of? If you're in
the middle of שחטing shecht a בהמה, beheima, the time it takes
to שחט shecht another בהמה, beheima, or if you're in the middle
of שחטing shecht a עוף, of, the time it takes to שחט
shecht another עוף? of? So would you say the time it takes
to do another שחיטה shechita, of the same type of animal you
are right now doing? או דלמא, o dilma, or would we say
אף בהמה לעוף? af beheima le-of? Even if you're שחטing shecht a
עוף, of, there is a standard time that creates a break, and
that is the time it takes to שחט shecht a בהמה, beheima.
which is obviously gives you a little bit you know more more
to play with. It takes longer to שחט shecht a בהמה. beheima.
Okay, so do you say a comparable act or do you say
you know a fixed amount of time? The time it takes to
שחט shecht a בהמה. beheima. או דלמא
אף בהמה לעוף. o dilma af beheima le-of. אמר להו, amar lehu,
he said to them, לא הוינא בדיחנא בי בחביבי דאשאליה. lo havni
bedichna bei be-chavivi de-ershayleh. Very interesting response. I was not like a
בדיחותא bedichuta is a joke, so בדיחנא bedichna here means I wasn't
like in good humor or like you know comfortable enough with my
with my relative. His relative here is his
uncle רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. רב Rav was the nephew of רבי
חייא, Rabbi Chiya, who was like right at the end of the
period of the תנאים of רבי, he was the one that sort
of compiled the תוספתא Tosefta etc. Presumably he learned this הלכה halacha.
from רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. And he said you know that's a
great question, but I wasn't sort of comfortable enough with רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya when he was teaching me this. He wasn't in a
good enough spirit or whatever we weren't on good enough terms whatever
the answer was that I wanted that I didn't feel like pressing
him with this question when he taught me this הלכה. halacha, So
I don't know the answer. Okay I heard this from רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, I never asked him that question, I don't know the
answer. אתמר. itmar. So although רב Rav now said he didn't know
the answer, he didn't get an answer from רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
now we're going to see that he himself does have an opinion
about it. אתמר, itmar, it was said, אמר רב, Amar Rav, the
same רב Rav said, כדי שחיטת בהמה לבהמה ועוף לעוף. k'dei shechitas
beheima le-beheima ve-of le-of. Okay,
so he actually did say that you go each animal for its
for the appropriate size, which by the way just means he's being
strict. Since he didn't know what the answer is, right? The question
would be that we should be lenient. We should say even if
you're שחטing shecht a עוף of we give you the time it
takes to שחט shecht the בהמה. beheima.
מן התורה min hatorah anyway. Well but he don't say that.
Okay anyway, even if you're שחטing shecht a עוף of we give
you the time it takes to שחט shecht a בהמה. beheima That
would be the opposite opportunity. Puzzle is so if he didn't know
maybe he's just being strict and saying okay so we have to
be strict and when you say if you're שחטing shecht a עוף
of it's the time it takes to שחט shecht a עוף, of,
which is a shorter time. That's what רב Rav says. ושמואל אמר,
ve-Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel was more lenient, אפילו בהמה לעוף. afilu beheima
le-of. Even the time it takes to שחט shecht a בהמה beheima.
if you're שחטing shecht? a עוף, of, that's always the fixed amount
of time that defines שהייה. shehiya וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבי
יוחנן, ve-chein ki atha Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, and similarly when רבין
Ravin came he said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
אפילו בהמה לעוף. afilu beheima le-of. That even you even when you're
שחטing shecht? a עוף of you have the time that you can
pause as long as it takes to שחט shecht. בהמה. beheima רבי
חנינא אמר, Rabbi Chanina amar, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says, כדי שיביא
בהמה אחרת וישחוט. k'dei she-yavi beheima acheres ve-yishchot. Not only to שחט
shecht? a בהמה beheima but to bring the בהמה beheima and שחט
shecht it. יביא, yavi, bring it, אפילו מעלמא? afilu me-alma? Even from
somewhere outside? נתת דבריך לשיעורין. nasata devareicha leshiurim. Who then then
you know you haven't given a fixed amount of time. It always
נתת דבריך לשיעורין nasata devareicha leshiurim means you've given your words over
for for different for different types of quantities. Meaning who knows? Is
the בהמה beheima in a market 10 feet away or is the
בהמה beheima in a market 10 miles away? Where you bringing your
בהמה behema, from? It's different for everybody. אמר פפא Amar Papa no
no no. We don't mean bring it from outside, but what we
mean is עומדת להטיל איכא בינייהו. omedes lehachil ita beinaihu.
Very interesting now we're getting a little bit to the graphic part
of or whatever the you know. of the שחיטה shechita, means it's
standing in front of you, but a standing cow isn't going to
do you any good. What do you have to do to שחט?
shecht You have to push it down on the floor and turn
it upside down. So what do you consider the time it takes
to שחט? shecht From the time your knife is on the neck
and just the time it takes to do that movement or from
the whole process? Now okay, admittedly the process doesn't begin getting a
cow from the market, but the process does begin you can conceivably
the cow's in front of you and you have to flip it
over and then שחט. shecht So do you include that in the
time in what's considered the time it takes to שחט? shecht So
that's a pretty reasonable position but that is obviously a much bigger
קולא kula than we've been talking about. Right, it's not the actual
act of שחיטה shechita, itself, correct? So that's a much bigger leniency
in terms of measuring this time.
Does
an animal need to be awake?
No. I mean the issue about stunning it or you know knocking
it out or those types of things. Like if you caught it
in its sleep would that count? Cow tipping. Cow tipping. Good point.
Yeah it doesn't have to be awake.
There's issues with stunning it then. What? What is the issue of
stunning it then?
Well the reason I mean I think that the opposition to stunning
it people gave הלכה you know answers and this came up I
mean it's even till today but it started 100 150 years ago
was this issue was was that it was I think it was
principally an opposition to having the you know secular law interfere because
as soon as you sort of grant the possibility that שחיטה shechita,
is not humane you know then you're then you're opening yourself up
to them saying that we won't allow it even to be done
with a knife and you know you have to שחט shecht it
our way and not your way. So the actual issue about you
know stunning and so on although there was a lot of תשובות
teshuvot written about how it's oops etc.
I think there are some concerns like maybe it makes it a
טריפה treifa or this or that but it was largely a concern
about letting secular law you know interfere with
הלכה.
Which means there really was no issue in the stunning then. Meaning
no issue with the secular they didn't care.
Yeah meaning if we were totally autonomous and we were just choosing
to do it ourselves and so on then might we choose choose
stunning? Yes. Is that necessarily right is that necessarily the best way
to do it for even for the well-being of the cow? I
don't know. I mean I think isn't those flipping flip over machines
isn't that what Temple Grandin says to do? Right? The machines that
they walk in and they just you know turn them upside down.
I was gonna say why isn't that a problem that if being
hitting a cow in the head to stun them which is what
they used to do is a problem why is flipping them upside
down not a problem? That can break their legs easily. Good question.
I don't know. I mean all those things the biggest problem you
could have is a טריפה treifa problem so yeah you have to
see if it could affect the טריפה. treifa. Okay maybe one of
these days we'll have a special I'm serious special שיעור put together
some of the like תשובות teshuvot around those issues because it's coming
up relevant right now. Okay so let's keep on going. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara says אמי
בי מר רב אמרי משמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. Ami bei Mar
Rav amrei mishmei de-Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina. They said in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael in the name of
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina כדי שיגביהנה וירביצנה וישחוט.
kedei she-yagbihena ve-yarbitzena ve-yishchot. So not flipping over interestingly they imagined again
it sounds like flipping over but it says lift it up and
cause it to crouch and שחט shechted. it. So I'm not exactly
understanding getting it did they did they not have it upside down
with the neck exposed? Did they take the knife underneath the neck?
You know that would be envisioned by the idea of crouching but
then why do they mention lift it up? Who needs to lift
it up?
So maybe lift it up so you can move their legs.
Oh is that what it is? Maybe. Can't do that with a
cow anyway.
I imagine it maybe ten guys.
Anyway okay but wouldn't you imagine the easier way to make something
crouch is to get at its legs and pull its legs? I
don't know.
Different goats you could do that.
I don't know. Anyway the anyway and then for so א aleph
it includes the process preparatory process and then it says דקה לדקה
וגסה לגסה. dakah le-dakah ve-gasah le-gasah. But then it's also more strict
on the second part of it because if it's a small animal
meaning a a sheep or a goat then the time it takes
to שחט shechted, a sheep or goat. If it's a large animal
meaning a cow the time it takes to שחט shechted a cow.
So on the one hand it's saying that you can't always go
by the cow time but on the other hand you do include
the time it takes to to prepare you know to begin the
process. And the גמרא Gemara. does not have a clear conclusion. רש״י
Rashi rules strictly. רש״י Rashi says that because of the debate and
because of whatever רב Rav in the end was strict that we
have to go by the stricter position and say if you're שוחט
shochet chickens then the amount of שהייה shehiya is only the time
it takes to שחט shechted a chicken and not including the preparatory
time. Okay אמר רבא Amar Rava השוחט בסכין רעה ha-shochet be-sakin ra-ah
if you're שוחט shechting with a dull knife. By the way notice
right we've always talked about knives with nicks because they tear but
you could have a dull knife that doesn't have a nick. It's
not tearing but it just doesn't slice so quickly. Right? It only
slices with one movement it only you know cuts a certain amount
deep and you have to keep on going back and forth till
it gets deeper which you could imagine is no fun for the
cow. So if you're שוחט shechting with a dull knife אפילו כל
היום כולו כשרה. afilu kol hayom kulo keshera. Even if it takes
you the whole day, it's exaggerated, it's כשר. kosher. But meaning שהייה
shehiya does not mean that the act of שחיטה shechita, has to
take a certain amount of time. שהייה shehiya is measure of interruption.
So if I have a dull knife and I have to go
back and forth and back and forth and my act of שחיטה
shechita. takes five minutes, again, one must imagine that the animal is
in pretty serious
pain or something
like that.
Right, but nevertheless, it's a כשר kosher act. There's no שהייה shehiya,
because there's no pausing, even though the act took a very long
time. Okay.
Sounds like it's a בדיעבד. bediavad.
Yeah, well that is true. Right, that's true. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava,
but again, this is interesting to note because everybody is, you know,
is always taught about how צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is
central and it might be central to the basic הלכה, but it's
interesting to note how it rarely, if ever, factors into any of
the הלכתי halachic formulations. So, you know, for better or worse, that
goes to a larger issue about the relationship of טעמי המצוות ta'amei
hamitzvot to the technical הלכתי halachic criteria and sometimes to what degree
do they or don't they impact, you know, some of these discussions.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
אפילו כמאן דאמר... afilu keman d'amar... בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. So רבא
Rava asks the following question.
שהיות מהו שיצטרפו? Shehiyot mahu sheyitzterfu? Can different little breaks combine? So
if you say that a break has to be 10 seconds, let's
say, let's say I took a one-second break, a four-second break, a
three-second break, a two-second break, okay, does that mean that I've had
a ten-second break, right, or does it, no, if it's a 10-second
break, it has to be a continuous 10 seconds, which you would
think, right, that creates an interruption that it's a continuous break. So
do those little breaks combine? So it says ותפשוט ליה מדידיה, U'tifshot
lei mididei, why don't you learn it out from your own example
about taking the whole day to שחט shechting with a dull knife?
Presumably that was a lot of little breaks. So the גמרא Gemara,
says no, התם דלא שהה, hatam d'lo shaha, that would be there
was never a break. You were just moving back and forth, you're
in constant motion. But what if you had tiny little breaks, would
that, would those combine? And it does not have a conclusion. בעי
רב הונא בריה דרב נתן. Ba'ei Rav Huna brei d'Rav Natan. שהה
במיעוט סימנים מהו? Shaha bemiut simanim mahu?
Let's say you did a שהייה shehiya. in the minority of the
סימנים, simanim, what's the law? And it says תיקו. teiku. Now this
exactly parallels what we did yesterday right before the משנה mishna where
it says where it said החליד במיעוט סימנים מהו hichlid bemiut simanim
mahu and רש"י Rashi reads these גמרות Gemaros in the simplest way
and again I'm going to repeat this because it's so fascinating I
think, which is you've already done a כשר שחיטה, kosher shechita, you
did רוב rov of both סימנים. simanim. If you were to stop
now, you'd be totally okay. But you didn't stop. You took a
break actually and then you finished. And רש"י Rashi says the point
here is that when we say רוב rov is ככולו, kekulo, but
that might mean that it's ככולו kekulo because that's as if you
did all. But if you went ahead and actually did all, that
becomes incorporated into your act. So even though if you were to
have stopped after you've done the majority of both and it would
have been a good שחיטה, shechita, because you chose to finish and
you finished in a bad way, that becomes incorporated into your act
and therefore it invalidates. So that would be the case if you
did שהייה במיעוט בתרא, shehiya bemiut batra, a שהייה shehiya. in the
last minority. רש"י Rashi says as a result of this, he says,
and I mentioned this yesterday, if a person שחטס shechts and then
sees that the animal is taking time for it to die and
it's suffering and you want to help put it out of its
suffering and you want to finish cutting, he says don't finish cutting
the normal way because then you would have done a שהייה, shehiya
right? You שחטד, you stopped, you saw it was taking time to
die. If you were now to resume and finish שחטינג, it would
be a שהייה. shehiya? So what you want to do is you
have to now, if you want to kill it, kill it in
a way that's not finishing, you know, cut it from behind, you
know, cut it, you know, cut the, cut the arteries and the
veins but don't finish the שחיטה, shechita that becomes a שהייה. shehiya,
So for רש"י, Rashi, he reads that that becomes, that that is
a problem, that that when you do the whole job even though
you could have stopped earlier it becomes incorporated. רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
disagrees, he has a different way of reading this גמרא. Gemara. He
basically reads this גמרא Gemara that it would be,
it's not exactly clear how he reads this גמרא, Gemara. but I
think he basically reads it that it would be the מיעוט miut
of the first סימן siman in a בהמה, meaning if I'm שחטינג
the trachea and the esophagus, so if I've done the trachea, I
finish the trachea with a שהייה shehiya and then I move on
to the esophagus. So that's where it might be incorporated. But after
I've completely done the שחיטה, shechita I've שחטד the trachea and the
majority of the esophagus, anything I do afterwards is inconsequential.
Just wait, wait, say the רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam read again? But
then why would it be a תיקו teiku if you did a
שהייה?
shehiya, Because again, you could have said that even if as far
as the trachea is concerned, I'm done with the trachea.
But according to רבינו תם...
Rabbeinu
Tam...
you did a מיעוט miut of the trachea?
No, you did a רוב rov of the trachea, you did שהייה,
you finished the trachea, and then you did the esophagus.
Why is that a, oh
you think, oh why isn't it then a שהייה for the esophagus?
Yeah, you're right, good point. I have to figure out what רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam says. The simple read is רש"י, Rashi, it's not
clear, I have to figure out again how רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
reads this גמרא. Gemara But רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam disagrees in principle.
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says the שהייה, any פסול after you've done
a כשר שחיטה kosher shechita should not be a problem. But רש"י
Rashi says no, if you choose to finish it, your פסולים psulim
can become a problem because that becomes incorporated into the act. Yeah,
you're right, Michael, I have to figure out what רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam is saying. Yeah, go ahead.
And the רש"י Rashi would permit after you've done the partial but
כשר שחיטה, kosher shechita, yeah, to do something else to the animal
before it's dead.
Like? Oh, you mean because you would make it a טריפה? treifa?
Yeah. No, you can't make it a טרפה treifa once it's שחט.
shechted Okay, it might not be dead.
Right, it might not be dead, but it's שחט, shechted so you
can't make it a טרפה. treifa. But that's a good point. The
other point you could have said was that of all the פסולים,
psulim, the problem of שהיה shehiya might be not so much the
פסול as that it says that the next act you're doing is
not connected to the earlier act; it's not part of the same
act. But if that were true, there wouldn't be a problem with
שהיה shehiya במיעוט בתרא, b'miut basra, because it would just say this
is a totally different act. So that's another point that's a חידוש
chiddush. according to רש״י. Rashi. Not only that what you do after
fifty-one percent is incorporated, but that even even though you had a
שהיה, shehiya, you could have waited an hour and done it, it's
still considered the same act with a שהיה, shehiya, rather than a
different act. That's also a חידוש. So, very interesting conceptual issues there
according to how we look at the last minority. Let's take and
finish this up, this משנה. mishna רבי שמעון אומר אם שהה כדי
ביקור. מאי כדי ביקור? Mai k'dei bikur? What does it mean, the
time it takes to check? אמר רבי יוחנן כדי ביקור של חכם.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan k'dei bikur shel chacham. The time it takes to
show it
to
a sage. So the גמרא Gemara says אם כן נתת דבריך לשיעורים.
Im kein natata devarecha l'shiurim. So again, you know, where's the sage?
If he's a block away, a mile away? אלא כדי ביקור טבח
חכם. Ela k'dei bikur tabach chacham. No, it means that the שוחט
shochet is a חכם. How long it would take you to check
your knife. Okay, so that is the issue of שהיה. shehiya. Now
we turn to this next משנה, mishna an issue about עיקור, ikur,
but also a go a very focused discussion about the difference between
טרפה treifa and נבילה. neveila. Let's take a look. שחט את הושט,
Shechat es ha-veshet, you שחט shechted the esophagus, ופסק את הגרגרת, u-pasak
es ha-gargeres, but then the the trachea got sort of cut, meaning
got uprooted from its place without an act of שחיטה. shechita That's
a פסול of עיקור. ikur. או פסק את הגרגרת, O pasak es
ha-gargeres, or the opposite order. First the trachea got uprooted, ואחר כך
שחט את הושט, v'achar kach shechat es ha-veshet, and then you שחט
shechted the esophagus. So again, it was a problem of עיקור ikur
and not שחט shechted one of the סימנים simanim correctly. או שחט
אחד מהן והמתין לו עד שמתה, O shechat echad mehen v'himtin lo
ad she-meisa, or you only שחט shechted one סימן siman and then
it just died. Okay, you never שחט shechting, the other סימן. siman.
Okay, so that's you didn't even really do an act of שחיטה,
shechita you only שחט one סימן. siman. או שהחליד את הסכין תחת
השני ופסקו, O she-hechlid es ha-sakin tachas ha-sheini u-psako, or after you
שחט one סימן siman you did חלדה, chalada, you שחט one סימן
siman normally and then you burrowed, you stuck the knife into the,
you know, side of the neck and you cut the other סימן
siman in the opposite direction. So that's the problem of חלדה, chalada,
of burrowing. So in all those cases, you ruined it while you
were doing the שחיטה. shechita. So רב ישבב Rav Yeshevav אומר—משום רבי
יהושע—I'm Rabbi Yehoshua, sorry, did I skip a line? רב ישבב אומר
נבילה. Rav Yeshevav omer neveila. It's a נבילה, neveila, because basically what's
a נבילה? neveila? An animal that died without a kosher שחיטה. shechita,
So in all these cases, it died without a kosher שחיטה. shechita,
רבי עקיבא אומר טרפה. Rabbi Akiva omer treifa. Rabbi Akiva said it's
a טרפה. treifa. Interesting. He said all the problems you did is
you wounded the animal. You wounded the animal and therefore you made
it a טרפה, treifa, which is okay, but it still died without
a שחיטה. shechita So Rabbi Akiva must say okay, but since but
you were doing an act of שחיטה, shechita it's not like it
just died of old age or died because it was attacked by
a lion. You did an act of שחיטה, shechita but you ruined
it. But since you were in the process of doing שחיטה, shechita,
we're not going to call it a נבילה; neveila; we're only going
to call it a טרפה, treifa, even though you didn't finish it.
Okay, so now but you'll see Rabbi Akiva reverses himself. So אמר
רב ישבב משום רבי יהושע. Amar Rav Yeshevav mishum Rabbi Yehoshua. So
רב ישבב said in the name of רבי יהושע, no, you're wrong,
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. כל שנפסלה בשחיטתה נבילה. Kol she-nipsala bi-shchitasah neveila.
If it became bad in the act of שחיטה, shechita. you ruined
the שחיטה, shechita then it's a נבילה. neveila. Okay, it doesn't matter
you were doing a שחיטה. shechita. If you didn't succeed in doing
the שחיטה, shechita. it's a
נבילה. neveila. כל ששחיטתה כראוי, Kol she-shchitasah k'ra'uy, if the שחיטה shechita
was kosher, ודבר אחר גרם לה ליפסל, v'davar acher garam lah le-hipasel,
and there was some external problem, like it had some puncture in
an organ, but the act of שחיטה shechita was a hundred percent,
טרפה, treifa, then that's a טרפה, treifa, but the שחיטה shechita has
to be good. והודה לו רבי עקיבא. V'hoda lo Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi
Akiva admitted, you know, he said you're right, that's a good way
of defining the difference, which is very strange because you always imagine
Rabbi Akiva, you know, as being like the smartest man in the
room.
Right, exactly. So that's actually quite interesting. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara שחט את הושט. Shechat es ha-veshet. So
you שחט the esophagus. והודה לו רבי עקיבא. V'hoda lo Rabbi Akiva.
Rabbi Akiva admitted, you know, you're right. If you have a problem
while you're שחט, it's a נבילה. neveila. Okay, so everybody agrees if
there's a problem in the trachea or the esophagus, it's a נבילה.
neveila. One minute. רמינהי. Remineihu. I'll ask you, אלו טרפות בבהמה. Elu
trefos b'vehema. The following are טרפות trefos in an animal. This is
from the next פרק, perek, which is all about טרפה. treifa. The
following are the טרפות: trefos: נקובת הושט, Nekuvos ha-veshet, if the esophagus
has a hole, even a small hole, ופסוקת הגרגרת, u-psukas ha-gargeres, and
if the trachea is cut, which we say it means the majority
is cut. Remember that the trachea is only טרפה treifa if the
if the majority of the trachea, the esophagus even a hole. But
regardless, what do you see? That if there's a cut in the
trachea or the esophagus, it's a טרפה. treifa. Now the גמרא Gemara
says one minute. We just had everybody agreeing that if you were
cutting the trachea and esophagus and ruined it, it's a נבילה, neveila,
not a טרפה. treifa. So how here are we calling it a
טרפה? treifa? Now I have to tell you that it took me
a while to read this גמרא Gemara because I'm saying like the
answer seems very obvious, which in the end the גמרא Gemara gets
to. Right, the answer seems like what—okay, our משנה mishna is that
you were... middle of cutting them, and then you sort of like,
the שחיטה shechita was never successful and then it died. That's a
נבילה. neveilah. The case of a טריפה treifa could be they had
a cut either from you or from somebody else, you know, naturally
or whatever, and then you did a totally kosher שחיטה. shechita So
since you did a kosher שחיטה, shechita it's not a נבילה, neveilah,
but because of these cuts it's a טריפה. treifa. So the גמרא
more or less says that at the end, but at this stage
it's not, and maybe one of the reasons it's not, which becomes
a little bit clearer later, is that it seems to be understanding
that if the trachea already has a cut in it or the
esophagus already has a cut in it, then when you come to
do your שחיטה, shechita you're not,
it's like the esophagus is no longer fit to do a שחיטה
shechita on, right? If the esophagus has a hole in it or
the trachea has a hole, then your שחיטה's shechita no longer meaningful.
So therefore, how is it ever even considered like you ever did
a שחיטה shechita, on an animal that already had a ruined trachea,
already had a ruined esophagus? So why isn't it just a נבילה?
neveilah? Okay, so that's the question. The answer will be along the
lines that I told you, but that is the question. If it
has a problem in the trachea or esophagus, it should never be
a kosher שחיטה, shechita, it should be a נבילה, neveilah, not a
טריפה. treifa. So let's see what the answer is.
What's the practical difference?
Oh, the practical difference is they're both אסור assur to eat, the
only difference is is whether it causes טומאה tumah or not. A
נבילה neveilah causes טומאה, tumah, טריפה treifa does not. You know, and
which prohibition you transgress, but they're both biblically prohibited. Yes. What could
you do?
Could you sell to a non-Jew?
Yes, yes, you could sell טריפות treifas and נבילות neveilahs to a
non-Jew. Okay, so the גמרא says, אמר רבא, amar Rava, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not
difficult, כאן ששחט ולבסוף פסק, kan sheshachat ulebasof pasak, כאן שפסק ולבסוף
שחט. kan shepasak ulebasof shachat. It depends when this cut in the
trachea and the esophagus occurred, before or after you began the שחיטה.
shechita. What does that mean? Let's take a look. שחט ולבסוף פסק,
shachat ulebasof pasak, let's say you shechted one סימן siman and then
the other סימן siman got a cut in it before you before
you got around to it, then נפסלה בשחיטה היא, nifsela bishchita hi,
then the שחיטה shechita, at least started correctly, it was totally whole
when you started the שחיטה. shechita The problem emerged in the middle
of the שחיטה. shechita That would be considered at least that the
שחיטה was okay and it's a טריפה. treifa. פסק ולבסוף שחט, pasak
ulebasof shachat, however, if it started with the cut in it and
then you began the שחיטה when already the סימנים, simanim, one of
the סימנים simanim were damaged, so did I just, no, I'm sorry,
I got exactly the opposite way. Excuse me. Let's do that again.
Okay. שחט ולבסוף פסק, shachat ulebasof pasak, if you started the שחיטה
correctly and then the damage occurred, נפסלה בשחיטה היא, nifsela bishchita hi,
then it's like your שחיטה was ruined because you were starting the
שחיטה correctly and some problem emerged, it got a cut, and therefore
it's like you never did a kosher שחיטה and it's a
נבילה. neveilah. פסק ולבסוף שחט, pasak ulebasof shachat, however, if it started
with the cut and then you did the שחיטה and presumably your
שחיטה you sort of started shechting where the hole already existed, so
כדבר אחר גרם לו ליפסל דמיא. kidavar acher garam lo lipasel damya.
It's like it's some other problem, not a שחיטה problem. I have
to tell you I really don't understand this.
I didn't really understand the question so much, I don't really understand
this answer. So anyway,
yeah,
somehow because it had the problem before you began, it's considered to
be a problem external to the שחיטה, whereas if the problem arose
during the שחיטה, it's a problem of ruining the שחיטה. Anyway, the
גמרא's going to reject it and I don't really understand it. איתיביה
רב אחא בר רב הונא לרבא. Esvei Rav Acha bar Rav Huna
leRava. So he asked him this, how could you say that it
matters the order? Our משנה mishna says, שחט את הושט ופסק את
הגרגרת, shachat et haveshet upasak et hagargeret, it says either you shechted
and then the גרגרת gargeret got uprooted or it had the reverse
order. פסק את הגרגרת ואחר כך שחט את הושט, pasak et hagargeret
veacharkach shachat et haveshet, first it got uprooted and then you did
and then you did the שחיטה, and in either case נבילה. neveilah.
It's a נבילה, neveilah, so it doesn't matter which order, if the
שחיטה got ruined, whichever order the סימנים simanim got, you know, damaged,
it's still going to be a נבילה. neveilah. So אימא, so he
says no, read the משנה mishna וכבר שחט את הושט. vekevar shachat
et haveshet. It means that if you, if it doesn't mean when
it says the גרגרת, gargeret, the trachea was damaged and then you
shechted the ושט, veshet, it doesn't mean then, it means you had
already shechted the ושט veshet מעיקרא meikara beforehand. So אמר ליה amar
lei he said back שתי תשובות בדבר, shtei teshuvot badavar, one minute,
two responses to that. חדא דהיי קמייתא, chada dehei kammaisa, then it's
exactly the first case of the משנה because exactly the difference between
the first and the second case is which happened first and which
happened second. ועוד התנן ואחר כך, veod hatnan veacharkach, you can't say
it means it already happened, the משנה says and then you shechted
it. Okay, so אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so anyway, that
was, as I said, I didn't even understand how that, what the,
I had a harder time understanding the question, I certainly didn't really
understand the answer that the order mattered, but now let's get to
answers that make a little more able to be understood in terms
of which is a נבילה neveilah which is a טריפה. treifa. אלו
אסורות קתני, Elu asurot ketani, you're right, the משנה that says that
lists these טריפות treifot and the damage to the trachea and esophagus,
it's not, they're not really טריפות. treifot. Really the משנה should be
understood to say the following problems make the animal forbidden. ויש מהם
נבילות ויש מהם טריפות. Veyesh mehem neveilot veyesh mehem treifot. Some are
נבילות, neveilot, some are טריפות. treifot. So basically he's admitting at this
stage that any damage to the trachea or the esophagus means that
the שחיטה was never valid, okay, and again you can, I think
this question, this position I think you can understand. If the trachea
esophagus is damaged, is cut, then it's never like you really did
a שחיטה *shechita*. So that's the assumption of the גמרא *Gemara*'s question.
If these are cut, you've never done a legitimate שחיטה *shechita*. So
how does the משנה *Mishna* call them a טרפה *trefa*? And the
answer is, you're right, the משנה *Mishna* doesn't literally mean טרפה *trefa*,
it means everything is forbidden, some are טרפות *trefas*, some are נבלות
*nevelas*. A damaged trachea and esophagus makes the animal a נבלה *nevela*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, that can't be. If it's listing
נבלות *nevelas*, well then there's a lot of other נבלות *nevelas* it
could list. דליחשב נמי דחזקיה *Deleihashev nami de-Chizkiya*. Chizkiya's statement. Remember this
from a few days ago, דאמר חזקיה נעשה גיסטרא נבלה *de-amar Chizkiya
naasa gistera nevela*. If you chopped it in half, it's a נבלה
*nevela*. Even if it's not, you know, why didn't it mention that
as long as we're talking about נבלות *nevelas*? וליחשב נמי דרבי אליעזר
*Veleihashev nami de-Rabbi Eliezer*. How about Rabbi Eliezer's statement? דאמר רבי אליעזר
נטלה הירך וחלל שלה נבלה *De-amar Rabbi Eliezer nittela hayerech vechalal shellah
nevela*. If the thigh together with the, you know, where it connects
to the socket is removed, that's a נבלה *nevela*. So if we're
listing נבלות *nevelas*, we should mention all נבלות *nevelas*. No, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says no. כי קתני נבלה דלא מטמיא מחיים *Ki katani
nevela dela mitamya mechayim*. We're talking about a נבלה *nevela* that only
it's a נבלה *nevela* once it dies. אבל נבלה דמטמיא מחיים *Aval
nevela demitamya mechayim*, these type of נבלות *nevelos*, chopped in half, missing
the thigh, that it causes טומאה *tuma*, it's a נבלה *nevela* while
it's still alive, לא קתני *lo katani*, aren't listed. Okay, so by
the way, this is interesting because remember when we discussed נבלה *nevela*,
the גמרא *Gemara* constantly was exchanging the term נבלה *nevela* and dead,
נבלה *nevela* and dead. Here the גמרא *Gemara* acknowledges that it could
be considered a נבלה *nevela* while it's alive because it's still breathing,
it's still whatever, the blood is still pumping. So which again raises
the question, so why are you calling it a נבלה *nevela* if
you're calling it alive? Okay, but this is very interesting in terms
of that earlier discussion about is definitions of נבלה *nevela* the same
as definitions of life and death. But anyway, he's saying we don't
want to discuss these bizarre cases where it's a נבלה *nevela* while
it's still alive. We're talking about something that's a נבלה *nevela* once
it dies. So yes, it does mention a damaged trachea and esophagus,
but not because that's a טרפה *trefa*, but because that ruins your
שחיטה *shechita* and would make it a נבלה *nevela*, but it doesn't
literally mean טרפה *trefa*. Okay, I just want to get, I know,
just one more line to get to actually an answer that's consistent
with how we understand it. So let's just read this. ריש לקיש
אומר *Resh Lakish omer*, and this is the answer that I think
we all would have said in the beginning. כאן ששחט במקום חתך
כאן ששחט שלא במקום חתך *Kan sheshachat bimkom chatach kan sheshachat shelo
bimkom chatach*. It matters whether the שחיטה *shechita* was good or not.
If it had a hole in the trachea and esophagus and you
שחט *shacht* in a different place, then your שחיטה *shechita* was good.
It just had a hole in the trachea and the esophagus. If,
however, you שחט *shacht* where this hole was, you never did a
good שחיטה *shechita*. So yes, it could have a hole in the
trachea and esophagus, but as long as you שחט *shacht* somewhere else
along the neck, you're doing a good שחיטה *shechita*. And the hole
in the trachea and esophagus just make it a טרפה *trefa*. If
you שחט *shacht* where the hole is, you didn't do a good
שחיטה *shechita* because then your hole was part of the cutting of
the thing and that was not part of an act of שחיטה
*shechita*. שחט במקום חתך *Shachat bimkom chatach*, if you cut where the
hole pre-existed, נפסלה בשחיטה היא *nifsala bishchita hi*.
Then that's a problem of your שחיטה *shechita* because your שחיטה *shechita*
incorporated this tear in the trachea and the esophagus. שלא במקום חתך
*Shelo bimkom chatach*, if it's not where the hole is, כי דבר
אחר גרם לה ליפסל *ki davar acher garam lah lipassel*, the שחיטה
*shechita* was 100 percent, there was just a different problem. There was
a hole in the trachea and esophagus, that's fine. That hole makes
it a טרפה *trefa*, but the שחיטה *shechita* was good and it
is not a נבלה *nevela*. So we will pick up here tomorrow
to continue
for this answer which is the first answer that I think is
really...